You never did eat your lunch , did you ?
I better get back to the office .
These extended lunch hours give my boss excess acid .
Why don 't you call your boss and tell him
you 're taking the rest of the afternoon off ?
Friday anyway , and hot .
What do I do with my free afternoon ? Walk you to the airport ?
Well , we could laze around here a while longer .
( SIGHS )
Ghegskeflmgymit time
Hotels of this sort aren 't interested in you when you come in ,
but when your time is up ...
Oh , Sam , I hate having to be with you in a place like this .
I 've heard of married couples who deliberately spend
an occasional night in a cheap hotel .
When you 're married you can do a lot of things deliberately .
You sure talk like a girl who 's been married .
Oh , Sam , this is the last time .
Yeah ? For what ?
For this .
For meeting you in secret so we can be secretive .
You come down here on business trips , and we steal lunch hours .
I wish you wouldn 't even come .
All right . What do we do instead ? Write each other lurid love letters ?
Oh , I have to go , Sam .
I can come down next week .
No .
Not even just to see you ? Have lunch , in public ?
Oh , we can see each other . We can even have dinner .
But respectably .
In my house , with my mother 's picture on the mantel
and my sister helping me broil a big steak for three .
And after the steak ,
do we send sister to the movies , turn Mama 's picture to the wall ?
Sam !
All right .
Marion , whenever it 's possible , I want to see you .
And under any circumstances , even respectability .
You make respectability sound disrespectful .
Oh , no , I 'm all for it .
It requires patience , temperance , a lot of sweating out .
Otherwise , though , it 's just hard work .
But if I can see you and touch you , even as simply as this , I won 't mind .
I 'm tired of sweating for people who aren 't there .
I sweat to pay off my father 's debts , and he 's in his grave .
I sweat to pay my ex-wife alimony ,
and she 's living on the other side of the world somewhere .
| Pay , too .
They also pay who meet in hotel rooms .
A couple of years and my debts will be paid off .
If she ever remarries , the alimony stops .
I haven 't even been married once yet .
Yeah . But when you do , you 'll swing .
Oh , Sam , let 's get married .
Yeah . And live with me in a storeroom behind a hardware store in Fairvale ?
We 'll have lots of laughs . I 'll tell you what .
When I send my ex-wife her alimony , you can lick the stamps .
I 'll lick the stamps .
Marion , you want to cut this off ,
go out and find yourself somebody available ?
I 'm thinking of it .
How could you even think a thing like that ?
Don 't miss your plane .
Hey , we can leave together , can 't we ?
I 'm late and you have to put your shoes on .
Is Mr. Lowery back from lunch ?
He 's lunching with the man who 's buying the Harris Street property .
You know , the oil lease man . That 's why he 's late . You got a headache ?
[ Tl pass .
Headaches are like resolutions ,
you forget them as soon as they stop hurting .
Have you got some aspirin ? I 've got something , not aspirin .
My mother 's doctor gave them to me the day of my wedding .
Teddy was furious when he found out I 'd taken tranquilizers .
Any calls ?
Teddy called me . My mother called to see if Teddy called .
Oh , your sister called to say she 's going to Tucson to do some buying
and she 'll be gone the whole weekend and ...
( HORN HONKING )
Wow .
It 's as hot as fresh milk .
Hey , you girls ought to get your boss to air condition you up .
He can afford it today .
( CHUCKLES )
Marion , will you get the copies of that deed ready for Mr. Cassidy ?
Yes , sir .
Tomorrow 's the day , my sweet little girl .
Oh , not you . My daughter .
A baby .
And tomorrow she stands her sweet self up there and gets married away from me .
I want you to take a look at my baby .
( CHUCKLES )
Eighteen years old
and she never had an unhappy day in any one of those years .
Come on , Tom . My office is air conditioned .
Do you know what I do about unhappiness ?
I buy it off .
Are ... Are you unhappy ?
Not inordinately .
I 'm buying this house for my baby 's wedding present .
$ 40,000 cash .
Now that 's not buying happiness . That 's just buying off unhappiness .
( CHUCKLES )
( MONEY FLAPPING )
I never carry more than I can afford to lose .
CASSIDY : Count them !
I declare !
I don 't . That 's how I get to keep it .
Tom , a cash transaction of this size is most irregular .
So what ? It 's my private money .
Now it 's yours .
Suppose we put it in the safe ,
and then Monday morning when you 're feeling good ...
Oh , speaking of feeling good ,
where 's that bottle you said was in your desk ?
Uh-oh !
( CHUCKLES )
You know , sometimes I can keep my mouth shut .
Lowery , I am dying of thirst-aroonie .
I don 't even want it in the office over the weekend .
Put it in the safe deposit box in the bank ,
and we 'll get him to give us a check on Monday instead .
Yes .
He was flirting with you .
I guess he must 've noticed my wedding ring .
LOWERY : Come in .
The copies . Mr. Lowery , if you don 't mind ,
I 'd like to go right on home after the bank .
I have a slight ... You go right on home .
Because me and your boss are going out
and get ourselves a little drinking done . Right ?
Of course . Do you feel ill ?
Just a headache .
What you need is a weekend in Las Vegas , the playground of the world .
I 'm going to spend this weekend in bed . Thank you .
Aren 't you going to take the pills ? They 'll knock that headache out .
Can 't buy off unhappiness with pills .
( SIGHS )
I guess I 'll go put this money in the bank and then go home and sleep it off .
( SAM 'S VOICE ) Marion , what in the world ... What are you doing up here ?
Of course I 'm glad to see you . I always am .
What is it , Marion ?
( BRAKES SQUEAK )
( STARTS ENGINE )
Hold it there .
In quite a hurry .
Yes . I didn 't intend to sleep so long .
I almost had an accident last night from sleepiness ,
so I decided to pull over .
You slept here all night ?
Yes . As I said , I couldn 't keep my eyes open .
There are plenty of motels in this area . You should 've ...
I mean , just to be safe .
I didn 't intend to sleep all night . I just pulled over . Have I broken any laws ?
No , ma 'am .
Then I 'm free to go ?
Is anything wrong ?
Of course not . Am I acting as if there 's something wrong ?
Frankly , yes .
Please , I 'd like to go .
Well , is there ?
Is there what ?
I 've told you there 's nothing wrong ,
except that I 'm in a hurry and you 're taking up my time .
( STARTS ENGINE )
Now , just a moment . Turn your motor off , please .
( TURNS OFF ENGINE )
May I see your license ?
Why ?
Please .
( STARTS ENGINE )
Be with you in a second !
I 'm in no mood for trouble . What ?
There 's an old saying . " The first customer of the day is always the most trouble . "
But like I say , I 'm in no mood for it ,
so I 'm gonna treat you so fair and square that you won 't have one human reason ...
Can I trade my car in and take another ?
Do anything you have a mind to . Being a woman , you will . That yours ?
Yes , it 's ... There 's nothing wrong with it .
I just ... Sick of the sight of it .
Why don 't you have a look around here
and see if there 's something that strikes your eyes .
And meanwhile , I 'll have my mechanic give yours the once-over .
You want some coffee ? I was just about ... No , thank you .
I 'm in a hurry and I just wananaa make a change .
One thing people never ought to be
when they 're buying used cars and that 's in a hurry .
But like I said , it 's too nice a day to argue . I 'll shoot your car in the garage here .
( CAR DOOR CLOSES )
( STARTS ENGINE )
That 's the one I 'd have picked for you myself .
How much ? Go ahead .
Spin it around the block .
It looks fine .
How much would it be with my car ?
You mean you don 't want the usual day and a half to think it over ?
You are in a hurry , aren 't you ? Somebody chasing you ?
Of course not . Please .
Well , it 's the first time the customer ever high-pressured the salesman .
I figure roughly
your car plus $ 700 .
$ 700 .
You always got time to argue money , huh ?
All right .
I take it you can prove that car is yours .
I mean , out-of-state license and all . You got your pink slip ...
I believe I have the necessary papers. ls there a ladies ' room ?
In the building .
Over there .
I think you better take it for a trial spin .
I don 't want any bad word of mouth about California Charlie .
I 'd really rather not . Can 't we just settle this and ...
I might as well be perfectly honest with you , ma 'am .
It 's not that I don 't trust you , but ...
But what ?
Is there anything so terribly wrong
about making a decision and wanting to hurry ?
Do you think I 've stolen my car ?
No , ma 'am .
All right , let 's go inside .
( STARTS ENGINE )
MAN : Hey !
Just put it in here , please .
Thank you .
CALIFORNIA CHARLIE 'S VOICE : Heck , Officer ,
that was the first time I ever saw the customer
high-pressure the salesman .
Somebody chasing her ?
OFFICER : I better have a look at those papers , Charlie .
CALIFORNIA CHARLIE : She look like a wrong one to you ?
OFFICER : Acted like one .
CALIFORNIA CHARLIE : The only funny thing , she paid me $ 700 in cash .
CAROLINE : Yes , Mr. Lowery .
LOWERY : Caroline , Marion still isn 't in ?
CAROLINE : No , Mr. Lowery , but then she 's always a bit late on Monday mornings .
LOWERY : Buzz me the minute she comes in .
And call her sister . No one 's answering at the house .
CAROLINE : I called her sister , Mr. Lowery , where she works ,
the Music Makers Music Store , you know ,
and she doesn 't know where Marion is any more than we do .
LOWERY : You better run out to the house .
She may be , well , unable to answer the phone .
CAROLINE : Her sister 's going to do that . She 's as worried as we are .
LOWERY : No , I haven 't the faintest idea .
As I said , I last saw your sister when she left this office on Friday .
She said she didn 't feel well and wanted to leave early , and I said she could .
That was the last I saw ... Oh , wait a minute .
I did see her some time later , driving ...
I think you 'd better come over here to my office , quick .
Caroline , get Mr. Cassidy for me .
After all , Cassidy , I told you , all that cash !
I 'm not taking the responsibility .
Oh , for heaven 's sake .
A girl works for you for 10 years , you trust her .
AH right , yes , you better come over .
CASSIDY : Well , I ain 't about to kiss off $ 40,000 !
I 'll get it back , and if any of it 's missing , I 'll replace it with her fine , soft flesh !
I 'll track her , never you doubt it .
LOWERY : Hold on , Cassidy .
I still can 't believe ... It must be some kind of a mystery . I can 't ...
You checked with the bank , no ? They never laid eyes on her , no ?
You still trusting ? Hot creepers ! She sat there while I dumped it out !
Hardly even looked at it . Planning . And even flirting with me !
( HONKING HORN )
Gee , I 'm sorry I didn 't hear you in all this rain .
Go ahead in , please .
Dirty night .
You have a vacancy ?
Oh , we have 12 vacancies . Twelve cabins , 12 vacancies .
They ... They moved away the highway .
Oh , I thought I 'd gotten off the main road .
I knew you must have .
Nobody ever stops here anymore unless they 've done that .
But there 's no sense dwelling on our losses .
We just keep on lighting the lights and following the formalities .
Your home address . Oh , just the town will do .
Los Angeles .
Cabin One . It 's closer in case you want anything .
Right next to the office .
I want sleep more than anything else , except maybe food .
Well , there 's a big diner about 10 miles up the road , just outside of Fairvale .
Am I that close to Fairvale ?
Fifteen miles . I 'll get your bags .
( UNLOCKING DOOR )
Boy , it 's stuffy in here .
Well , the mattress is soft
and there 's hangers in the closet and stationery with Bates Motel printed on it
in case you wanna make your friends back home feel envious .
And the ...
Over there .
The bathroom .
Yeah .
Well , if you want anything , just tap on the wall .
I 'll be in the office . Thank you , Mr. Bates .
Norman Bates .
You 're not really gonna go out again and drive up to the diner , are you ?
No .
Well , then would you do me a favor ? Would you have dinner with me ?
I was just about to myself .
You know , nothing special , just sandwiches and milk .
But I 'd like it very much if you 'd come up to the house .
I don 't set a fancy table , but the kitchen 's awful homey .
I 'd like to . All right .
You get yourself settled and take off your wet shoes ,
and I 'll be back as soon as it 's ready .
Okay .
With my ... With my trusty umbrella .
( LAUGHS )
MRS. BATES : No ! I tell you no !
I won 't have you bringing strange young girls in for supper !
By candlelight , I suppose , in the cheap , erotic fashion
of young men with cheap , erotic minds !
NORMAN : Mother , please .
MRS. BATES : And then what , after supper ? Music ? Whispers ?
NORMAN : Mother , she 'sjust a stranger . She 's hungry and it 's raining out .
MRS. BATES : " Mother , she 's just a stranger . "
As if men don 't desire strangers . As if ...
( SHUDDERING ) I refuse to speak of disgusting things , because they disgust me !
You understand , boy ? Go on .
Go tell her she 'll not be appeasing her ugly appetite
with my food or my son !
Or do I have to tell her ' cause you don 't have the guts ?
Huh , boy ? You have the guts , boy ?
NORMAN : Shut up ! Shut up !
( DOOR OPENS )
( DOOR CLOSES )
I 've caused you some trouble .
No .
Mother ... My mother ...
What is the phrase ?
She isn 't quite herself today .
You shouldn 't have bothered . I really don 't have that much of an appetite .
Oh , I 'm sorry .
I wish you could apologize for other people .
Don 't worry about it .
But as long as you 've fixed a supper , we may as well eat it .
It might be nicer and warmer in the office .
Well , it stopped raining .
Eating in an office is just too officious .
( CHUCKLES )
I have the parlor back here .
All right .
Sit down .
Thank you .
You 're very kind .
It 's all for you . I 'm not hungry . Go ahead .
You ... You eat like a bird .
And you 'd know , of course .
No , not really .
Anyway , I hear the expression " Eats like a bird "
is really a false ... Falsity .
Because birds really eat a tremendous lot .
But I don 't really know anything about birds .
My hobby is stuffing things .
You know , taxidermy .
And I guess I 'd just rather stuff birds because
I hate the look of beasts when they 're stuffed .
You know , foxes and chimps .
Some people even stuff dogs and cats , but , oh , I can 't do that .
I think only birds look well stuffed because ...
Well , because they 're kind of passive to begin with .
It 's a strange hobby . Curious .
Uncommon , too .
Oh , I imagine so .
And it 's not as expensive as you 'd think . It 's cheap , really .
You know , needles and thread , sawdust .
The chemicals are the only thing that cost anything .
A man should have a hobby .
Well , it 's ... It 's more than a hobby .
A hobby 's supposed to pass the time , not fill it .
Is your time so empty ?
No .
Well , I run the office
and tend the cabins and grounds
and do little errands for my mother .
The ones she allows I might be capable of doing .
Do you go out with friends ?
Well , a boy 's best friend is his mother .
You 've never had an empty moment in your entire life , have you ?
Only my share .
Where are you going ?
I didn 't mean to pry .
I 'm looking for a private island .
What are you running away from ?
Why do you ask that ? I don 't know .
People never run away from anything .
The rain didn 't last long , did it ? You know what I think ?
I think that
we 're all in our private traps ,
clamped in them , and none of us can ever get out .
We scratch and claw ,
but only at the air , only at each other .
And for all of it , we never budge an inch .
Sometimes we deliberately step into those traps .
I was born in mine . I don 't mind it anymore .
Oh , but you should . You should mind it .
Oh , I do , but I say I don 't .
You know , if anyone ever talked to me the way I heard ,
the way she spoke to you ...
Sometimes when she talks to me like that ,
I feel I 'd like to go up there and curse her and leave her forever .
Or at least defy her .
But I know I can 't .
She 's ill .
She sounded strong .
No , I mean ill .
She had to raise me all by herself , after my father died .
I was only five and it must 've been quite a strain for her .
I mean , she didn 't have to go to work or anything like that .
He left her a little money .
Anyway , a few years ago , Mother met this man .
And he talked her into building this motel .
He could have talked her into anything .
And when he died , too , it was just too great a shock for her .
And the way he died ...
( CHUCKLES )
I guess it 's nothing to talk about while you 're eating .
Anyway , it was " just too great a loss for her . She had nothing left .
Except you .
Well , a son is a poor substitute for a lover .
Why don 't you go away ?
To a private island , like you ?
( SIGHS )
No , not like me .
I couldn 't do that . Who 'd look after her ?
She 'd be alone up there .
Her fire would go out .
It 'd be cold and damp like a grave .
If you love someone ,
you don 't do that to them , even if you hate them .
You understand , I don 't hate her .
I hate what she 's become .
I hate the illness .
Wouldn 't it be better if you put her
some place ...
You mean an institution ? A madhouse ?
People always call a madhouse " some place , " don 't they ?
Put her in some place .
I 'm sorry . I didn 't mean it to sound uncaring .
What do you know aboutcaflng ?
Have you ever seen the inside of one of those places ?
The laughing and the tears
and the cruel eyes studying you .
My mother there ?
( CHUCKLES ) But she 's harmless .
She 's as harmless as one of those stuffed birds .
I am sorry .
I only felt ... It seems she 's hurting you .
I meant well .
People always mean well .
They cluck their thick tongues and shake their heads
and suggest , oh , so very delicately .
Of course , I 've suggested it myself .
But I hate to even think about it .
She needs me .
It 's not as if she were
a maniac , a raving thing .
She just goes a little mad sometimes .
We all go a little mad sometimes .
Haven 't you ?
Yes .
Sometimes just one time can be enough .
Thank you .
Thank you , Norman .
Norman .
Oh , you 're not going back to your room already ?
I 'm very tired .
And I have a long drive tomorrow , all the way back to Phoenix .
Really ?
I stepped into a private trap back there
and I 'd like to go back and try to pull myself out of it
before it 's too late for me , too .
Are you sure you wouldn 't like to stay just a little while longer ?
Just for talk ?
Oh , I 'd like to , but ...
All right .
Well , I 'll see you in the morning . I 'll bring you some breakfast , all right ?
What time ?
Very early . Dawn .
All right , Miss ...
Crane .
Crane . That 's it .
Good night .
( DOOR OPENS )
( DOOR CLOSES )
( RUMMAGING )
( GLASS CLINKING )
( SIGHS )
( UNWRAPPING SOAP )
( SCREAMING )
No !
( CONTINUES SCREAMING )
( HIGH-PITCHED SCREAMING )
( PANTING )
( SHOWER CONTINUES RUNNING )
NORMAN : Mother ! Oh , God , Mother !
Blood ! Blood !
( SHOWER CONTINUES RUNNING )
( STARTS ENGINE )
( CAR PASSING BY )
( TURNS ENGINE OFF )
( SLOSHING )
( GURGLING )
( GURGLING CONTINUES )
( AIR BUBBLES POPPING )
WOMAN : I 've tried many brands .
So far , of those I 've used , I haven 't had much luck with any of them .
Let 's see what they say about this one .
They tell you what its ingredients are
and how it 's guaranteed to exterminate every insect in the world ,
but they do not tell you whether or not it 's painless .
And I say , insect or man , death should always be painless .
I suppose , this one seems to claim more and better
qualities than lots of the others .
Sam ?
Sam ! Lady wants to see you .
Yes , miss ?
I 'm Marion 's sister .
Oh , sure . Lila .
Is Marion here ?
Well , of course not . WOMAN : Thank you .
Something wrong ?
( CASH REGISTER RINGS )
She left home on Friday .
I was in Tucson over the weekend and I haven 't heard from her since .
Not even a phone call .
Look , if you two are in this thing together , I don 't care , it 's none of my business ,
but I want to talk to Marion and I want her to tell me
it 's none of my business and then I 'll go ...
Bob , run out and get yourself some lunch , will you ?
That 's okay , Sam . I brought itwith me .
Run out and eat it .
SAM : Now , what thing could we be in together ?
LILA : Sorry about the tears .
Well , is Marion in trouble ? What is it ?
MAN : Let 's all talk about Marion , shall we ?
Who are you , friend ?
My name is Arbogast , friend .
I 'm a private investigator .
Where is she , Miss Crane ?
I don 't know you .
Why , I know you don 't , because if you did , I wouldn 't be able to follow you .
What 's your interest in this ?
Well , $ 40,000 .
$ 40,000 ? That 's right .
Well , one of you 'd better tell me what 's going on , and tell me fast .
I can take just so much of this ...
Now , take it easy , friend .
Take it easy . It 's just that your girlfriend stole $ 40,000 .
What are you talking about ? What is this ?
She was supposed to bank it on Friday for her boss and she didn 't .
And no one has seen her since .
Someone has seen her .
Someone always sees a girl with $ 40,000 .
Sam , they don 't want to prosecute , they just want the money back .
Sam , if she 's here ...
She isn 't . She isn 't .
Miss Crane , can I ask you a question ?
Did you come up here on just a hunch and nothing more ?
Not even a hunch . Just hope .
Well , with a little checking I could get to believe you .
I don 't care if you believe me or not .
All I want to do is see Marion before she gets in this too deeply .
Did you check in Phoenix ? Hospitals ? Maybe she had an accident , or a holdup .
No , she was seen leaving town in her own car ,
by her employer , I might add .
I can 't believe it . Can you ?
Well , you know , we 're always quickest to doubt people
who have a reputation for being honest .
I think she 's here , Miss Crane .
Where there 's a boyfriend ...
Well , she 's not back there with the nuts and bolts ,
but she 's here , in this town somewhere .
I 'll find her . I 'll be seeing you .
( INAUDIBLE )
( CAR APPROACHING )
Evening . Evening .
I almost drove right past .
I 'm always forgetting to turn the sign on , but we do have a vacancy .
Twelve , in fact . Twelve cabins , twelve vacancies . Candy ?
No , thanks .
Last two days , I 've been to so many motels my eyes are bleary with neon ,
but , you know , this is the first place that looks like it 's hiding from the world .
Well , I 'll tell you the truth . I didn 't really forget to turn the sign on .
Just doesn 't seem like any use anymore , you know .
See , that used to be the main highway right there .
Well , wanna come in and register ?
No , no , sit down . I don 't wanna trouble you .
I just wanna ask a few questions .
No , that 's no trouble . Today 's linen day .
I always change the beds here once a week whether they 've been used or not .
Hate the smell of dampness , don 't you ? It 's such a ...
I don 't know , creepy smell . Come on .
You out to buy a motel ?
No .
Reason I ask , you said you 'd seen so many
in the past couple of days , I thought maybe you ...
What ... What was it you wanted to ask ?
Well , you see , I 'm looking for a missing person .
My name 's Arbogast . I 'm a private investigator .
I 've been trying to trace a girl
that 's been missing for , oh , about a week now from Phoenix .
It 's a private matter . The family wants to forgive her .
She 's not in any trouble .
I didn 't think the police went looking for people who aren 't in trouble .
I 'm not the police . Oh , yeah .
We have reason to believe that she came along this way .
May have stopped in the area . Did she stop here ?
Well , no one 's stopped here for a couple of weeks .
Would you mind looking at the picture before committing yourself ?
Commit myself ?
You sure talk like a policeman .
Look at the picture , please .
Sure ? Yeah .
Well , she may have used an alias .
Marion Crane 's her real name ,
but she could 've registered under a different one .
Well , I tell you , | don 't even much bother with guests registering anymore .
You know , one by one , you drop the formalities .
I shouldn 't even bother changing the sheets ,
but Old habits die hard .
Which reminds me ...
What 's that ?
It 's the light . The sign .
We had a couple last week , said if the thing hadn 't been on ,
they would 've thought this was an old , deserted ...
Well , you see , that 's exactly my point .
You said that nobody 'd been here for a couple weeks ,
and there 's a couple came by and didn 't know that you were open .
Yeah .
Well , as you say , old habits die hard .
It 's possible , this girl could 've registered under another name .
Do you mind if I look at your book ?
Thank you . No .
All right .
I 'll get the date somewhere .
See , there 's nobody .
Let 's see now , I have a sample of her handwriting here .
Oh , yes .
Here we are .
Marie Samuels . That 's an interesting alias .
Is that her ?
Yeah . Yeah , I think so .
Marie , Marion .
Samuels . Her boyfriend 's name is Sam .
Was she in disguise , by any chance ?
Wanna check the picture again ?
Look , | wasn 't lying to you , Mr ...
Oh , I know that . I know you wouldn 't lie .
You know , it 's tough keeping track of the time around here .
Oh , I know , I know .
Oh , yeah .
Well , it was raining
and her hair was all wet .
I tell you , it 's not really a very good picture of her either .
No , I guess not .
Tell me all about her .
Well ,
she arrived rather late one night , and she went straight to sleep
and left early the next morning .
How early ?
Oh , very early .
Mmm-hmm .
Which morning was that ?
The ...
The next morning . Sunday .
I see . | \ / | I 'T1l 'T1 — halTTfl \ lTT1 .
Did anyone meet her here ? No .
Did she arrive with anyone ?
No .
Did she make any phone calls or ...
Locally ?
Did you spend the night with her ? " ?
No .
Well then , how would you know that she didn 't make any phone calls ?
( STAMMERING )
Well , she was very tired and ...
See , now I 'm starting to remember .
I 'm making a mental picture of it in my mind .
You know , if you make a mental picturization of something ...
That 's right . That 's right . Take your time .
She was ... She was sitting back there ...
No , no , she was standing back there with a sandwich in her hand
and she said she had to go to sleep early
because she had a long drive ahead of her .
Back where ? Back where she came from .
No , you said before that she was sitting back there ... Standing back there ...
Yes , back in my parlor there .
She was very hungry and I made her a sandwich
and then she said that she was tired and she had to go right to bed .
I see . How did she pay you ?
Cash ? Check ? Cash .
Cash , huh ?
And after she left , she didn 't come back ?
Well , why should she ?
Yeah .
THQAT )
Well , Mr. Arbogast , I guess that 's about it .
I 've got some work to do , if you don 't mind .
Well , to tell you the truth , I do mind .
You see , It It doesn 't jell , it isn 't aspic , and this ain 't jelling .
It 's not coming together . Something 's missing .
Well , I don 't know what you could expect me to know .
People just come and go , you know .
That 's right . She isn 't still here , is she ?
No .
If I wanted to check the cabins , all 12 of them ,
I 'd need a warrant , wouldn 't I ?
Listen , if you don 't believe me , come on with me . You can help me change beds .
Okay ? Oh . No , thanks .
Change your mind ?
You know , I ... I think I must have one of those faces you just can 't help believing .
Is anyone at home ? No .
Oh ? There 's somebody sitting up in the window .
No , no , there isn 't .
Sure , go ahead . Take a look .
Oh , that must be my mother .
She 's an invalid .
It 's practically like living alone .
Oh , I see .
Now , if this girl , Marion Crane , were here , you wouldn 't be hiding her , would you ?
Not even if she paid you well ? No .
No .
Let 's just say , just for the sake of argument ,
that she wanted you to gallantly protect her .
You 'd know that you were being used .
You wouldn 't be made a fool of , would you ?
But I 'm not a fool . Well , I ...
And I 'm not capable of being fooled , not even by a woman .
Well , this is not a slur on your manhood .
Let 's put it this way .
She might have fooled me , but she didn 't fool my mother .
Well , then your mother met her . Could I talk to your mother ?
No . As I told you , she 's confined .
Yes , but just for a few minutes . That 's all .
There might be some hint that you missed out on .
You know , sick old women are usually pretty sharp .
Mr. Arbogast ... I think I 've ...
Just for a moment . I wouldn 't disturb her .
I think I 've talked to you all I want to .
Yes , but just for ...
I think it 'd be much better if you left now . Thanks .
Well , all right .
You sure would save me a lot of leg work if you 'd let me talk to her .
Would I need a warrant for that , too ?
Sure .
All right . Thanks anyway .
( STARTS ENGINE )
( CAR PULLS AWAY )
Hello , Loomis . This is Arbogast. ls Lila there ?
Okay . Let me talk to her , please .
Hello , Lila .
Lila , listen . Marion was up here .
Yes , she spent last Saturday night at the Bates Motel .
It 's right out here on the old highway .
I even know what cabin she was in. ltwas number one .
Well , this young fella that runs the place said that she just spent the night ,
left the next day and that was it .
No , not exactly .
Well , I did question him , believe me , but I think I got all there was to get .
I 'll just have to pick up the pieces from here .
Well , I tell you , I don 't feel entirely satisfied ...
See , this boy had a sick old mother .
I think she saw Marion and talked to her .
No . No , unfortunately , he wouldn 't let me see her .
Well , I was , but I think I 'll go back to the motel first .
No , you stay there with Loomis . I 'll be back in about an hour .
All right , fine . Listen , I ...
You 'll be happy to know what I think .
I think our friend Sam Loomis didn 't know that Marion was here .
Yeah . All right . See you in about an hour or less .
All right , bye-bye .
Bates ?
( ARBOGAST SCREAMS )
Sometimes Saturday night has a lonely sound .
Ever notice that , Lila ?
Sam , he said an hour or less .
Yeah .
( SIGHS ) It 's been three .
Well , are we just going to sit here and wait ?
He 'll be back .
Let 's sit still and hang on , okay ?
How far is the old highway ?
You wanna go out there , don 't you ?
Bust in on Arbogast and the old lady ... Yes .
Maybe shake her up . Yes !
That wouldn 't be a wise thing to do .
Patience doesn 't run in my family , Sam .
I 'm going out there . Look , Arbogast said ...
An hour , or less .
Well , I 'm going .
You 'll never find it .
Stay here .
Why can 't I go with you ?
I don 't know . One of us has to be here , in case he 's on the way .
What am I supposed to do , just sit here and wait ?
Yeah . Stay here .
Arbogast ?
Arbogast !
( ECHOING ) Arbogast !
( CAR APPROACH ES )
( CAR STOPS )
( DOOR OPENING )
He didn 't come back here ?
Sam !
No Arbogast , no Bates . Only the old lady at home .
Sick old lady unable to answer the door , or unwilling .
Where could he have gone ?
Maybe he got some definite lead . Maybe he went right on .
Without calling me ?
In a hurry .
Sam , he called when he had nothing . Nothing but a dissatisfied feeling .
Don 't you think he 'd have called if he had anything at all ?
Yes , I think he would 've .
Let 's go see Al Chambers .
Who 's he ?
Our deputy sheriff around here .
All right . Let me get my coat .
Good evening .
Well , I don 't know where to start , except at the beginning .
Yes .
This is Lila Crane from Phoenix .
How do you do ?
She 's been here searching for her sister .
There 's this private detective helping and ...
Well , we got a call from this detective
saying that he 'd traced her to that motel out on the old highway .
That must be the Bates Motel .
He traced her there and called us to say he was going to question Mrs. Bates .
Norman took a wife ?
SAM : No , I don 't think so . An old woman . His mother .
Well , anyway , that was early this evening . We haven 't seen or heard from him since .
Now , your sister 's missing how long ?
Well , she left Phoenix a week ago yesterday , without a trace .
How 'd you and this detective come to trace her to Fairvale ?
They thought she 'd be coming to me .
Left Phoenix under her own steam ?
Yes .
She 's not missing so much as she 's run away .
SAM : That 's right .
From what ?
She stole some money .
SHERIFF : A lot ?
$ 40,000 .
And the police haven 't been able to ...
Everyone concerned thought if they could get her to give the money back ,
they could avoid involving her with the police .
That explains the private detective . He traced her to the Bates place .
What exactly did he say when he called you ?
Well , he said that Marion was there for one night and then she left .
With the $ 40,000 ?
Well , he didn 't say anything about the money .
It isn 't important what he said on the phone , is it ?
He was supposed to come back here and talk to us
after he talked to the mother , and he didn 't .
That 's what I want you to do something about .
Like what ?
I 'm sorry if I seem overanxious .
It 's just that I 'm sure there 's something wrong out there and I have to know what .
Well , I think there 's something wrong too , miss , but not the same thing .
I think what 's wrong is your private detective .
I think he got himself a hot lead as to where your sister was going ,
probably from Norman Bates ,
and called you to keep you still while he took off after her and the money .
No , no , he said he was dissatisfied and he was going back there .
Why don 't you call Norman and let him sayjust what happened ?
SHERIFF : At this hour ?
Well , he was out when I was there just a while ago .
If he 's back , he probably isn 't even in bed yet .
He wasn 't out when you were there ,
he just wasn 't answering the door in the dead of night , like some people do .
This fellow lives like a hermit .
You must remember that bad business out there about 10 years ago .
Please . Call .
Florrie , the Sheriff wants you to connect him with the Bates Motel .
Hello , Norman ? Sheriff Chambers .
I 've been just fine , thanks .
Listen , we got worries here .
Yeah , have you had a fella stop by there tonight ...
Well , this one wouldn 't be a customer , anyway .
He 's a private detective , name of ...
Arbogast .
And after he left ?
No , that 's okay , Norman .
( HANGS UP PHONE )
This detective was there , Norman told him about the girl ,
the detective thanked him and he went away .
And he didn 't come back ? He didn 't see the mother ?
Your detective told you he couldn 't come right back
because he was going to question Norman Bates ' mother , right ?
Yes .
Norman Bates ' mother has been dead and buried
in Green Lawn Cemetery for the past 10 years .
I helped Norman pick out the dress she was buried in . Periwinkle blue .
SHERIFF : It ain 't only local history , Sam .
It 's the only case of murder and suicide on Fairvale ledgers .
Mrs. Bates poisoned this guy she was involved with
when she found out he was married .
Then took a helping of the same stuff herself .
Strychnine . Ugly way to die .
Norman found them dead together .
( WHISPERING ) In bed .
You mean that old woman I saw sitting in the window out there wasn 't Bates ' mother ?
Now , wait a minute , Sam . Are you sure you saw an old woman ?
Yes ! In the house behind the motel !
I called and pounded but she just ignored me !
You want to tell me you saw Norman Bates ' mother ?
But it had to be because Arbogast said so , too !
And the young man wouldn 't let him see her because she was too ill .
Well , if the woman up there is Mrs. Bates ,
who 's that woman buried out in Green Lawn Cemetery ?
Now , Mother , I 'm gonna bring something up ...
( MRS. BATES LAUGHS )
MRS. BATES : I am sorry , boy ,
but you do manage to look ludicrous when you give me orders .
NORMAN : Please , Mother .
MRS. BATES : No ! I will not hide in the fruit cellar .
( MRS. BATES LAUGHS )
You think I 'm fruity , huh ?
I 'm staying right here .
This is my room and no one will drag me out of it ,
least of all my big , bold son .
NORMAN : They 'll come now , Mother .
He came after the girl , and now someone will come after him .
Mother , please , it 's just for a few days .
Just for a few days so they won 't find you .
MRS. BATES : Just for a few days ?
In that dark , dank fruit cellar ? No !
You hid me there once , boy , and you won 't do it again , not ever again !
Now get out !
I told you to get out , boy .
NORMAN : I 'll carry you , Mother .
MRS. BATES : Norman , what do you think you 're doing ?
Don 't you touch me ! Don 't ! Norman !
Put me down ! Put me down ! I can walk on my own .
( CHURCH BELL RINGING )
( INDISTINCT CHATTER )
Good morning . Good morning .
Good morning .
We thought if you didn 't mind , we 'd drive out to that motel with you .
He 's already been .
Went out before service .
Did you two have breakfast ?
You didn 't find anything ?
Nothing . Let 's clear the way here .
Well , what did he say about my sister ?
Just what he told your detective , she used a fake name .
Saw the register myself .
Saw the whole place , as a matter of fact . That boy 's alone there .
No mother ?
You must have seen an illusion , Sam .
I know you 're not the seeing-illusions type ,
but no woman was there and I don 't believe in ghosts ,
so there it is . I still feel that there 's something ...
Can see you do . I 'm sorry I couldn 't make you feel better .
You want to come around to my office this afternoon
and report a missing person and a theft , that 's what you want to do .
The sooner you drop this in the lap of the law ,
that 's the sooner you stand a chance of your sister being picked up .
How about that ?
I don 't know .
It 's Sunday .
Come on over to the house and do your reporting around dinnertime .
It 'll make it nicer .
You too , Sam .
Thank you .
Maybe I am the seeing-illusions type .
No , you 're not .
Well , you want me to drop you at the hotel or ...
Sam .
I still won 't feel satisfied until I go out there .
Neither will I. Come on .
We better decide what we 're gonna say or do when we walk in there .
We 're going to register as man and wife .
We 're going to get shown to a cabin ,
and then we 're going to search every inch of the place , inside and out .
( CAR DOOR OPENS )
I wonder where Norman Bates does his hermiting .
Someone 's at that window . I just saw the curtain move .
Come on .
Well ?
Just coming up to ring for you .
Uh-huh .
Suppose you want a room .
We were gonna try to make it straight to San Francisco ,
but we don 't like the look of that sky .
Looks like a bad day coming , doesn 't it ?
Okay .
I 'll take you to Cabin 10 .
Better sign in first , hadn 't we ?
No . That 's not necessary .
My boss is paying for this trip and , well , it 's 90 % business .
He wants practically notarized receipts .
I 'd better sign in and get a receipt .
Thank you .
I 'll get your bags . Haven 't any .
I 'll show you the room , then .
SAM : First time I 've ever seen it happen .
You check in any other place in this country without bags
and you have to pay in advance .
$ 10 .
( PAPER CRINKLING )
SAM : That receipt .
I 'll go on ahead .
NORMAN : All right , there 's your receipt . Now , I 'll show you the cabin .
Don 't bother yourself . We 'll find it .
Sam , we have to go into that cabin and search it ,
no matter what we 're afraid of finding or how much it may hurt .
I know .
Do you think if something happened , it happened there ?
I don 't know .
But if you had a useless business like this motel ,
what would you need to get out ?
To get a new business somewhere else ?
$ 40,000 ?
How could we prove that ...
Well , if he opens a motel on the new highway in , say , a year ...
There must be some proof that exists now ,
something that proves he got that money away from Marion somehow .
What makes you sound so certain ?
Arbogast . He liked me , Sam .
Or he felt sorry for me and he was beginning to feel the same way about you .
I could tell the last time I talked to him on the phone .
He wouldn 't have gone anywhere
or done anything without telling us , unless he was stopped .
And he was stopped . So he must have found out something .
We 'll start with Cabin One .
If he sees us , we 're just taking the air .
Bates .
No shower curtain . Sam !
Look ! What is it ?
It 's figuring . It didn 't get washed down . Look .
Some figure has been added to or subtracted from 40,000 .
That proves Marion was here .
It 'd be too wild a coincidence ...
Bates never denied she was here .
Well , doesn 't that prove that he found out about the money ?
Do we simply ask him where he 's hidden it ?
No .
But that old woman , whoever she is , she told Arbogast something .
I want her to tell us the same thing .
You can 't go up there .
Why not ?
Bates . Well , let 's find him .
One of us can keep him occupied while the other gets to the old woman .
You 'll never be able to hold him still if he doesn 't want to be held .
I don 't like you going into that house alone .
I can handle a sick old woman .
All right , I 'll find Bates and keep him occupied .
Wait a minute .
If you get anything out of the mother ,
can you find your way back to town ?
Yes , of course .
If you do get anything , don 't stop to tell me .
You looking for me ?
Why , yes , as a matter of fact .
Wife 's taking a nap
and I never can keep quiet enough for her ,
so I just thought I 'd look you up and talk .
Good . You satisfied with your cabin ?
Oh , it 's fine .
I 've been doing all the talking so far , haven 't I ?
I thought it was the people who were alone most of the time
who did all the talking when they got the chance .
Here you are doing all the listening .
You are alone here , aren 't you ? Mmm-hmm .
Drive me crazy .
I think that would be a rather extreme reaction , don 't you ?
Just an expression .
What I meantwas I 'd do just about anything to get away .
Wouldn 't you ? No .
( KNOCKING ON DOOR )
Mrs. Bates ?
( GASPS )
( SIGHS )
I 'm not saying you shouldn 't be contented here ,
I 'm just doubting that you are .
I think if you saw a chance to get out from under , you 'd unload this place .
This place ? This place happens to be my only world .
I grew up in that house up there . I had a very happy childhood .
My mother and I were more than happy .
You look frightened . Have I been saying something frightening ?
I don 't know what you 've been saying .
I 've been talking about your mother , about your motel .
How you gonna do it ?
Do what ?
Buy a new one in a new town where you won 't have to hide your mother .
Why don 't you just get in your car and drive away from here , okay ?
Where will you get the money to do that , Bates ?
Or do you already have it socked away ?
Shut up !
A lot of it . $ 40,000 .
I bet your mother knows where the money is and what you did to get it .
I think she 'll tell us .
Where 's that girl you came here with ? Where is she ?
Mrs. Bates ...
( SCREAMING )
( FOOTSTEPS )
( NORMAN SCREAMING )
I 'm Norma Bates !
( SCREAMING )
( PEOPLE CHATTERING )
If anyone gets any answers it 'll be the psychiatrist .
Even I couldn 't get to Norman and he knows me .
You warm enough , miss ? Yes .
Did he talk to you ?
No .
I got the whole story , but not from Norman . I got it from his mother .
Norman Bates no longer exists .
He only half-existed to begin with .
And now the other half has taken over ,
probably for all time .
Did he kill my sister ?
Yes .
And no .
Well , now look , ifyou 're trying to lay some psychiatric groundwork
for some sort of plea , this fellow would like to cop ...
A psychiatrist doesn 't lay the groundwork .
He merely tries to explain it .
But my sister is ... FRED : Yes .
Yes , I 'm sorry .
The private investigator , too .
If you drag that swamp somewhere in the vicinity of the motel , you 'll ...
Have you any unsolved missing persons cases on your books ?
Yes , two .
Young girls ?
Did he confess to ...
Like I said , the mother .
Now , to understand it the way I understood it , hearing it from the mother ,
that is , from the mother half of Norman 's mind ,
you have to go back 10 years
to the time when Norman murdered his mother and her lover .
Now , he was already dangerously disturbed ,
had been ever since his father died .
His mother was a clinging , demanding woman ,
and for years the two of them lived as if there was no one else in the world .
Then she met a man ,
and it seemed to Norman that she threw him over for this man .
Now , that pushed him over the line and he killed them both .
Matricide is probably the most unbearable crime of all ,
most unbearable to the son who commits it .
So he had to erase the crime , at least in his own mind .
He stole her corpse .
A weighted coffin was buried .
He hid the body in the fruit cellar ,
even treated it to keep it as well as it would keep .
And that still wasn 't enough .
She was there , but she was a corpse .
So he began to think and speak for her ,
give her half his life , so to speak .
At times he could be both personalities , carry on conversations .
At other times , the mother half took over completely .
He was never all Norman , but he was often only Mother ,
and because he was so pathologically jealous of her ,
he assumed that she was as jealous of him .
Therefore , if he felt a strong attraction to any other woman ,
the mother side of him would go wild .
When he met your sister ,
he was touched by her , aroused by her .
He wanted her .
That set off the jealous mother , and Mother killed the girl .
After the murder , Norman returned as if from a deep sleep ,
and , like a dutiful son , covered up all traces of the crime
he was convinced his mother had committed !
Why was he dressed like that ?
He 's a transvestite .
Not exactly .
A man who dresses in women 's clothing in order to achieve a sexual change
or satisfaction is a transvestite .
But in Norman 's case , he was simply doing everything possible
to keep alive the illusion of his mother being alive .
And when reality came too close ,
when danger or desire threatened that illusion ,
he 'd dress up , even to a cheap wig he bought .
He 'd walk about the house , sit in her chair , speak in her voice .
He tried to be his mother .
And now he is .
That 's what I meant when I said I got the story from the mother .
You see , when the mind houses two personalities ,
there 's always a conflict , a battle .
In Norman 's case , the battle is over ,
and the dominant personality has won .
And the $ 40,000 ? Who got that ?
The swamp . These were crimes of passion , not profit .
He feels a little chill . Can I bring him this blanket ?
Oh , sure . All right .
( NORMAN AS MRS. BATES ) Thank you .
MRS. BATES : It 's sad when a mother has to speak the words
that condemn her own son ,
but I couldn 't allow them to believe that I would commit murder .
They 'll put him away now , as I should have years ago .
He was always bad ,
and in the end he intended to tell them I killed those girls and that man ,
as if I could do anything except just sit and stare ,
like one of his stuffed birds .
They know I can 't even move a finger , and I won 't .
I 'll just sit here and be quiet , just in case they do suspect me .
They 're probably watching me . Well , let them .
Let them see what kind of a person I am .
I 'm not even gonna swat that fly .
I hope they are watching . They 'll see .
They 'll see and they 'll know ,
and they 'll say , " Why , she wouldn 't even harm a fly . "
( TOW CHAIN CLINKING )